A Guide to the Papers of Robert Whitehead, 1958-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Robert Whitehead 1958-1960
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6409-c
Ca. 500 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. .5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Ann Whitehead Thomas, Round Hill, Virginia, on January 24, 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Robert Whitehead was born in Lovingston, Virginia, on September 21, 1897, and was educated at Lovingston, Lynchburg High School, and the University of Virginia, graduating with a law degree. He married Myra Loving McGinnis and served in the armed services during World War I. Whitehead served as the Commonwealth's Attorney of Nelson County, 1933-1941, Democrat Elector, 7th Virginia District, 1936, Virginia State Chairman, Truman Barkley Straight Ticket Committee, 1948, and Democratic member of the House of Delegates from 1942-1960. He was also the director of The First National Bank of Nelson County, and belonged to the Episcopal Church, the Raven Society, Omicron Delta Kappa, Tau Kappa Alpha, Rotunda Club, Ruritan, American Legion, and Executive Committee of the Virginia State Bar.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Robert Whitehead (1897-1960), a member of the Virginia House of Delegates from Nelson County, Virginia, who represented Amherst and Nelson counties, consists of his alphabetical file for the years 1958-1960, ca. 500 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. .5 linear feet). Whitehead's files are a mixture of constituent correspondence, letters between himself and colleagues in the Virginia General Assembly, news clippings and other information about possible bills and proposals coming up before the General Assembly.
Contents List
- Correspondence - A 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: alcohol and liquor by the drink, the apple tax, law governing flashing lights and sirens on volunteer fire department vehicles, Francis Pickens Miller, Fitzgerald Bemiss, House Democratic Caucus, Accountants Society of Virginia.
- Correspondence - American Cyanamid Company 1959-1960 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - B 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: sale of the electrical facilities of Virginia Polytechnic Institute to the town of Blacksburg, billboard proposal, boat law, banking, possible boy scout camp in Nelson County, and John E. Burnley application for the restoration of his citizenship rights with a letter from Lindsay Almond about Burnley.
- Correspondence - C 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: aviation taxation, changes to the Charlottesville City Charter, Hardy C. Dillard, J.B.M. Carter, responsibility of railroads to maintain their right of ways, and the Virginia Civil War Commission Centennial Center.
- Correspondence - D 1959-1960, Topics or correspondents include: John H. Daniel, driver license requirements, Leon Dure, education issues, including massive resistance and integration, Hampton Roads improvements, Ted Dalton, Colgate W. Darden, Jr., drunk driving bill, "dump" bill, Harry B. Davis and segregation. (Box 1)
- Correspondence - E-F 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: salary of school board members, Literary Fund, hotel and motel tax, death by wrongful act, election laws, Burr P. Harrison, bonds, J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., road financing, education committee vacancies, Garnett S. Moore, Orby L. Cantrell, C. Harrison Mann, Jr.
- Correspondence - G 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: gasoline shrinkage and evaporation losses to retail gasoline dealers in Virginia, W.E. Garnett and the proposal for the establishment of an Interracial Commission, Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries, J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., and Samuel P. Goodloe.
- Correspondence - H, I, J 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: Literary Fund, Highway Department, state income taxes, Certified Public Accountants regulatory bill, E. Blackburn Moore, C.W. Cleaton, and Omer L. Hirst.
- Correspondence - K, L 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: Certified Public Accountants regulatory bill, Burr P. Harrison, labor and the minimum wage, higher education, Roads and Internal Navigation Commission, and Literary Fund.
- Correspondence - M, N, O 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: car insurance, George C. Marshall Memorial Address by Wilbur C. Hall, Committee on Insurance and Banking, James Monroe Bicentennial Committee, motor vehicle laws, medical examiner fees, criticism of Charlottesville Redevelopment and Housing Authority decisions about minority housing, sanitary milk control, and a bill for the relief of James S. Nicholas.
- Correspondence - Motor Vehicle Responsibility Act 1958-1960 (Box 1)
- Correspondence - P 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  Topics or correspondents include: Certified Public Accountants regulatory bill, bill to make polio vaccine compulsory in Virginia, Lewis F. Powell, Jr., Charles R. Fenwick, and Harold H. Purcell.
- Correspondence - R-S 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  Topics or correspondents include: railroad laws, Louis D. Rubin, state revenue and allocations, sales tax and related tax bills, Melvin L. Shreves, W. Roy Smith, R. Maclin Smith, St. Paul's Men's Association, sterilization, and Harry F. Byrd, Sr. concerning the Stonewall Jackson Memorial.
- Correspondence - T, U, V 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  Topics or correspondents include: B.P. Thornhill, Jr., the Sunday closing statute, the sales tax proposal, the measurement of timber and the Doyle Rule, and educational television, sale of the electrical facilities of Virginia Polytechnic Institute to the town of Blacksburg.
- Correspondence - W, X, Y, Z 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  Topics or correspondents include: John C. Webb, sales tax proposal, educational television, J. Harvie Wilkinson, Jr., J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., tax increases.